Jack Hamm Illustration collection, Inclusive: 1941-1960, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Jack Hamm Illustration collection
Inclusive: 1941-1960, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
155
Browne, P. D. (Philip Dale); Hamm, Jack
1 document box
The Jack Hamm Illustration collection includes original drawings, art prints, and newspaper clippings of Hamm’s work in cartoons and religious illustrations.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Philip Dale (P.D.) Browne taught in the Texas Education System as well as conducted research on the Civil War, specifically in the Freestone County, Texas area. He worked at Seventh and James Baptist Church and later was a mathematics and religion teacher at Baylor University, both in Waco, Texas.
Jack Beaumont Hamm was born March 5, 1916, in Wichita, Kansas. He studied in Chicago at the Moody Bible Institute and the Frederick Mizen Art Academy. Lack of funds contributed to his leaving school and pursuing other work, notably at Newspaper Enterprise Association (NEA) in Cleveland, Ohio, as a cartoonist. Hamm also served in the Army with stops in Alaska and the Aleutian Islands.
Hamm enrolled at Baylor University and created content for the Baylor Lariat (student newspaper) and Round-Up (yearbook). He graduated in 1948 and was immediately hired by the university as an art instructor and as the University Designer.
In 1950, Jack Hamm started Religious Drawings, Inc. to distribute his ministry through art. In his Waco studio, he created a weekly religious cartoon for more than 700 newspapers in 45 states and at least 17 foreign countries, an audience he estimated to be more than 29 million. In 1961, Hamm left Baylor to become the Staff Artist for the Baptist Standard and moved his studio to Dallas, Texas. Eventually, he also became an instructor at Dallas Baptist College (now University).
Jack Hamm was married to the former Dorisnel Alexander and had four children. Hamm died December 22, 1996, in Dallas, Texas. He is buried in the Gordo City Cemetery in Gordo, Alabama.
Scope and Content
The Original Drawings series includes pencil drawings as well as pen and ink drawings created by Hamm for use in advertising and in the Centennial Edition (1945) of the Baylor University Round-Up (yearbook). The Prints and Clippings series is made up of art prints and newspaper clippings which provide a reference to the types of work Hamm created. The art prints are primarily religious in nature and were created and distributed through Religious Drawings, Inc. The newspaper clippings were created while Hamm was a student and instructor at Baylor. The clippings have been retained on newsprint to provide a view of his work as originally intended.
Arrangement
The collection was previously arranged by item type and content. Current arrangement is in two series: I. Original Drawings and II. Prints and Clippings.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 155. Acquired 1970-04-24
Related Resources
Related references
“Around the State.” Baptist Standard. 2008 December 10.
“Artist Jack Hamm Joins Faculty of Baylor Next Fall.” Waco Tribune-Herald (Waco, Texas). 1948 July 11.
Find A Grave, Inc. “Jack Hamm.” Memorial #128120570. Databases. Accessed 2021 June 10.
“Hamm, Jack.” Lambiek Comiclopedia. Accessed 2021 June 10.
“Religious Cartoonist Wins High Award: Freedom Foundation Picks Jack Hamm’s ‘Relay’ Drawing.” The Baytown Sun (Baytown Texas). 1953 February 21.
Ryan, Terry Jo. “Baylor Grad Jack Hamm Combined Faith With Love of Illustrating.” Waco Tribune-Herald (Waco, Texas). 2008 November 22.
“Wacoan named Artist for Baptist Standard.” Waco News-Tribune (Waco, Texas). 1961 March 1.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Hamm, Jack 1916-1996 -- Caricatures and Cartoons.; Hamm, Jack 1916-1996.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- Faculty.
Subjects
Christian life -- Pictorial works.; Christian literature -- Publishing.; Editorial cartoons.; Illustrators -- Texas.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Drawings.; Prints.
- Original Drawings, circa 1945, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Original Drawings series is dated circa 1945 with undated materials. The undated materials are pencil drawings created while Jack Hamm was employed in Cleveland, Ohio, and represented by Artists’ and Literary Agent Bertha Klausner, located in New York City. The dated materials are pen and ink drawings created for use in the Baylor University yearbook. Hamm was a student at Baylor when these were created. The series is arranged in chronological order and in good condition.
  - Secular, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baylor Round-Up, Centennial Edition, circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Baylor Round-Up, Centennial Edition, circa 1945 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 1)
- Prints and Clippings, 1941-1960, undated; 2
  The Prints and Clippings series is dated 1941-1960. Stupe the Student was a regular column in the Lariat for which Hamm wrote and created an illustration. Other items are primarily religious in nature, created by Religious Drawings, Inc., while Hamm's studio was in Waco. Original newspaper clippings have been retained for context and intended appearance. The series is arranged in chronological order and is in good condition.
  - Prints: Religious (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Prints: Religious (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings: Baylor Lariat, Stupe the Student, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: Baylor Lariat, 1952- 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: General Newspapers, 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Prints: Religious, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Prints: Religious, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Prints: Religious, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Prints: Religious, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Prints: Religious, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)